Beth: Speech, language and communication
might all sound the same, but they
actually have unique meanings.
Speech generally refers to the act of
speaking, and someone with a problem
with speech may have trouble with
hearing or saying specific sounds
or understanding patterns of words.
Language refers to the ability
to communicate through speech by
delivering and receiving meaningful
messages through reading, or hearing.
A child that has problems with language
may not use proper sentence construction
and grammar or may have trouble
deciphering complex sentences or thoughts.
Communication can be verbal or
non-verbal using body language.
It may involve the use of sarcasm,
gestures, or facial expressions which
give an indication of the meaning of what
someone is trying to communicate to them.
Most people learn to communicate from
birth, however, if that development is
slowed down or interrupted, a child may
not learn about watching and listening to
people when they are talking, the meaning
of words, or how to hold a conversation.
When communication does not develop
as expected it makes it hard to
understand what people are saying,
say what you want or feel, and the
world can seem a very scary place.
An individual may then decide to
withdraw into their own little world.
Speech and language delays have
many possible causes, but they
are known to accompany Autism.
In some instances, however, more than
one factor may cause this, for instance,
dyslexia and other learning disabilities
can lead to language delays in some cases
and often this co-exists with Autism.
Children with Autism can
find it hard to relate to and
communicate with other people.
They might be slower to develop
language, have no language at all.
They may have significant problems
with understanding or using spoken
language and are not always able
to use gestures to make up for
the problems they have with words.
In addition to late speech, there are
a number of other communication-related
issues that relate to autism.
In general, children with autism are
more likely to be slow to respond
to their name or other verbal
attempts to gain their attention
They may speak only in single words
or repeat certain phrases over and
over, seeming unable to combine words
into meaningful sentences, or repeat
words or phrases that they hear.
They may use words that seem odd, out
of place, or have a special meaning
known only to those familiar with
the child's way of communicating.
They may also learn to communicate
in different ways like using
pictures or their own sign language.